בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody.
Today’s דף daf is ס"ג, Samech Gimmel, sixty-three. We’re at the bottom
of ס"ב עמוד ב. Samech Bet Amud Bet. Yesterday we looked at
the very important debate of אביי ורבא Abaye and Rava about עובד
מאהבה ומיראה oved me'ahava umiyirah where interesting position of the רמב"ם Rambam
he thinks it somehow means fear of the God but that’s still
not belief in the
God but the simple understanding is you're doing it for exterior motives
and how much is an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara when
it’s not in the context of actual worship, actually it is an
act of worship but it’s not a worship that is based on
belief. And that is the debate of אביי ורבא Abaye and Rava
and רבא Rava says they are actually exempt. And what we actually
discussed yesterday is and why then is anything ever an issue of
martyrdom, of יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareig ve'al ya'avor since it's not coming
with belief? And in a way actually you could ask the question
even forgetting that debate, I'm just reviewing what we said yesterday, that
if you’re being compelled to do it then you’re not liable for
doing it because you’re forced, it’s an אונס. ones. So
basically ראשונים Rishonim say תוספות Tosafot says, other ראשונים Rishonim say that
the act of martyrdom is a מצוה mitzvah of martyrdom, number one,
even if after you do it you’re exempt from that act because
you were forced, but what you did was you violated or you
did not fulfill your obligation of martyrdom and in this case of
עבודה זרה avoda zara it might not technically be עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. We discussed that converting to Islam isn’t עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
Islam is not an עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and the מצוה mitzvah
of martyrdom is not whether technically it’s עבודה זרה avoda zara or
not, but it’s the issue about renouncing your Judaism and accepting another
faith, it’s from the מצוה mitzvah of ואהבת את ה' אלקיך. Ve'ahavta
es Hashem Elokecha. So that was one interesting thing. But within the
issue of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, אביי Abaye says, רבא Rava says
that it’s not enough that it’s expressed as an act of worship
as far as everybody externally is concerned, it has to be coming
from a position of belief
and that’s in contrast to when a person doesn’t realize they’re in
front of an idol or believes they’re just showing honor but not
an act of worship, doesn’t treat the idol as a god. All
of those things everybody would agree, even אביי Abaye would agree, that’s
not an act of worship. But as an act of worship without
the attendant belief in the person’s mind, that’s the area of debate.
So that was a fascinating issue we saw yesterday. And then we
also saw this whole major discussion about whether if a person does
multiple forms of worship of עבודה זרה avoda zara in one state
of forgetfulness, how many sin offerings do they bring, חטאות. chata'ot. By
שבת, Shabbos, if you forget that it’s שבת, Shabbos, no matter how
many מלאכות melachot you do you bring one. But if you remember
it’s שבת Shabbos but forget the individual מלאכה melacha you bring a
separate one for each מלאכה. melacha. That’s a principle called חילוק מלאכות.
chiluk melachot. Each מלאכה melacha is distinct. And by עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, first there was a ברייתא braisa of רב זכאי Rav Zakkai
that sounded like we don’t hold like that, even if you do
זיבוח, קיטור, ומנסך, zivuach, kitor, umenaseich, etc., it’s all just one. רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan did not like that, he rejected that, he said
we have a principle of חילוק עבודות. chiluk avodot. And now we
have another ברייתא braisa that seems to be
that might have been saying the same thing, also רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan rejected it. So where we pick up right now, yes, David
you have a question. Right.
Does Islam say that it’s actually the same God as our God?
Well look, as I said, that depends on what you mean by
saying God. They tell a different story about the God. If it’s
a worship of another God, it does not have to be through
images. The question is how different is that God concept to say
it’s a worship of another God? I mean even within Jews, between
רמב"ם Rambam and the kabbalists they probably sound to a lot of
people like they’re talking about a different
God. So the assumption is that Islam by the vast majority of
the פוסקים poskim and ראשונים Rishonim is that it is not a
different God, it is the same God with a different story about
the God. Who is the God’s primary people, who is the God’s
primary prophet or latest prophet and so on, but it’s still fundamentally
the worship of the same God. Alright, but so that’s the issue
there. Alright, so now back to this. Okay, so the question at
hand was we had a ברייתא braisa that said שבת Shabbos is
different than other עבירות. aveyrot. And one contrast it was was that
other עבירות aveyrot are different than שבת. Shabbos. שבת Shabbos is different
than other עבירות aveyrot is more weighty because שבת Shabbos multiple מלאכות
melachot are multiple חטאות, chata'ot, which is not the same with other
עבירות. aveyrot. So the only thing that fit for was עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. That seems to say by עבודה זרה avoda zara separate
acts of עבודה avoda is only one sin offering. That supports that
idea that it’s one sin offering. But that didn’t fit with the
end of the ברייתא, braisa, because the end of the ברייתא braisa
said that by שבת Shabbos if you do something by other עבירות
aveyrot you do something unintentionally you still bring a קרבן. korban. By
שבת Shabbos you do something unintentionally you don’t bring a קרבן. korban.
Now that’s bizarre. We would think you bring a קרבן korban in
both cases. So הגמרא haGemara says it certainly doesn’t work by עבודה
זרה avoda zara because עבודה זרה avoda zara the way you do
an עבודה זרה avoda zara unintentionally is that you think that there’s
no prohibition, איסור. issur. But by שבת Shabbos and then you bring
the sin offering. But by שבת Shabbos the same would be true
if you didn’t know about the איסור issur of שבת Shabbos you
would bring the sin offering. So saying this issue about the difference
between multiple... offering and one if you do multiple עבודות avodos doesn't
fit with the end of the ברייתא. braisa. Okay, and that's where
we come up with in the גמרא. Gemara. So we leave off
with
the following. מאי קשיא Mai Kushya it is 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10 about 12 lines from the bottom, line of ס"ט ע"ב,
Samech-Tes Amud Beis, starts with the line למאן דאמר. L'man De'amar. So
it says like this: מאי קשיא. Mai Kushya. Now why is that
difficult? That I can say that there is a case where you're
a שוגג shogeg by עבודה זרה avodah zarah and you bring a
sin offering and by שבת Shabbos you don't. What's the case? דילמא
לעולם אימא לך, Dilma Le'olam Eima Lach, רישא Reisha I'm sorry, not
by עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but by some other sin. דילמא לעולם
אימא לך, Dilma Le'olam Eima Lach, I will tell you, רישא בעבודת
כוכבים, Reisha ba-avodas kochavim, the beginning of the ברייתא braisa that said
multiple sin offerings versus one, that's עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Multiple מלאכות
melachos on שבת Shabbos is multiple sin offerings, multiple עבודות avodos by
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is one sin offering. That works. Okay, if
you can buy into the idea that there's not חילוק עבודות chiluk
avodos by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The סיפא, seifa, the סיפא seifa
in the end where it makes a difference about whether you bring
it all in a case of שוגג, shogeg, is בשאר מצוות, bishar
mitzvos, is not talking about עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It's contrasting שבת
Shabbos to other מצוות. mitzvos. Fine. How would this work by other
מצוות? mitzvos? What is that contrast?
בשוגג בלא מתכוון דקסבר Beshogeg b'lo miskaven d'kasavar now here's the example
by other מצוות mitzvos רוקו ובלעו. Roku u-valo'o. Let's say you got
something in your mouth, something liquidy and you think it's your spit
and you swallow it. Okay, that's the other מצוות, mitzvos, that's like
a מצווה mitzvah of eating forbidden foods. Okay, and it turns out
that it was actually forbidden fat. Okay, now that was a case
that you would still have to bring a sin offering, even though
you thought you weren't even eating something, just thought you were swallowing
your spit. מה שאין כן בשבת, Mah she'kein bishabbos, now something analogous
by שבת, Shabbos, what's the פטור patur example? What's the case? שנתכוון
להגביה את התלוש וחתך את המחובר. Sheniskaven l'hagbi'ah es ha-talush v'chatach es
ha-mechubar. You thought you were just going to pick up a blade
of grass you saw lying on the ground, a dandelion, you thought
it was already cut from no longer growing, and you thought you
would just pick it up, and in the act of picking it
up you actually plucked it from the ground. Now the comparison of
these two cases is this is basically considered not just שוגג shogeg
but מתעסק. misasek. שוגג shogeg means you knew, you did exactly the
act you thought you were doing, but you made some mistake. What
was the mistake? You were going to eat this piece of forbidden
fat, but you actually thought it was permissible to eat forbidden fat.
That's one thing, a mistake in law. Or it could be a
mistake in facts. You thought this was steak and it turned out
to be forbidden fat. But nevertheless it's considered the same act because
you wanted to eat something and you ate something. That's a normal
שוגג. shogeg. That you bring a sin offering by שבת Shabbos and
a sin offering by other עבירות. aveiros. But then there's something called
מתעסק. misasek. You were trying to do one act and you did
a completely different one. Okay, eating this type of food or that
type of food is not considered completely different. Okay, for example you
thought you were swallowing your spit and it turned out that you
were eating a fat, you know, you were eating some food. That's
seen as a that's seen as a completely different you could just
say, "hey, you wanted to put something down your throat." Okay, now
it's not just the difference of drinking versus eating. Okay, it's the
idea that somehow swallowing your own spit is like a natural type
of a bodily function as opposed to taking something that was external
to the body, putting it in and ingesting it and eating it.
Then it's a question how exactly where do you define the line,
but I think at a at a certain at a certain like,
you know, anthropological level we would sort of say that those are
different things. Would you say, "Oh did you eat something? Did you
drink anything today?" "No." "Ha, liar! You swallowed your spit, you drank
water." No, give me a break. You don't call that drinking, right?
That's a different act. Okay, so that's considered like מתעסק. misasek. You
actually trying to do something else. I went out to shake my
hands with you and accidentally my hand turned on the light switch
on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, that is not like an error, that's a
מתעסק. misasek. I was trying to do a completely different act. Alright,
so by שבת Shabbos if I thought I was if I thought
I was cutting one blade of grass and I wound up cutting
another or something of that nature character, or let's say, here's even
a different example, תוספות Tosafos gets into this a lot of details
about this, okay, I'm not going to get into the level of
detail, but let's say I thought I was cutting this blade of
grass but I thought it wasn't growing from the ground anymore and
it turned so but I was doing an act of cutting, I
knew I was doing an act of cutting, and it turned out
it was growing from the ground. It was still growing and you
kind of "No, I thought it was already cut." Okay, I thought
I was snipping off the top of it and it had already
been cut and it was no longer growing from the ground and
it turned out that I actually detached it from the ground. Okay,
that might be a classic שוגג, shogeg, okay, because I was trying
to do an act of cutting and I did. But in this
case I thought I was just picking something up and it turns
out that I cut it off of the ground. That's מתעסק. misasek.
So the point, the difference is like this: by שבת Shabbos and
actually not just unique by שבת, Shabbos, it's really true by all
עבירות, aveiros, you're exempt by מתעסק. misasek. It's not even if from
a קרבן, korban, it's not just an error, it's like you didn't
even do the act you were trying to do, it's not even
associated with you. You're completely exempt from it. The one exception to
that by מתעסק... misasek... is by forbidden fat foods and forbidden sexual
intercourse. Okay, and there you are not exempt even if you're trying
to do something completely different from a sin offering. You don't, you're
not intentional, okay, but it's still considered enough your act that you
bring a sin offering as opposed to everything else. So let's read
that. Okay,
so שוגג בלא מתכוון, shogeg belo miskavein, it's not just שוגג, shogeg,
it's לא מתכוון, lo miskavein, like you weren't even trying to do
that act.
Okay. רוקו ובולעו. roko uvolo. מצינו גבי שבת דפטור, matzeinu gavi Shabbos
depatur, שנתכוון להגביה את התלוש, sheniskavein lehagbi'ah es hatolush, you were just
trying to pick up something that was already detached, והגביה וחתך את
המחובר, vehigbi'ah vechasach es hamichubar, what you wound up doing was cutting
something that was attached. פטור. Patur. Okay. Now והא רב נחמן אמר
שמואל, veha Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, like Rav Nachman said Shmuel, דאמר
de'amar who says המתעסק hamis'asek really the exception here is in שבת,
Shabbos, it's funny because the purpose of the ברייתא braisa is to
say שבת Shabbos is different from all the other עבירות. aveiros. But
here שבת Shabbos is the rule. The exception is eating forbidden fat
foods or forbidden sexual acts. המתעסק בחלבים ובעריות, hamis'asek bechalavim uva'arayos, if
somebody makes an is just incidental by their acts that they're doing
by חלבים chalavim which is fats but it really means forbidden foods
and forbidden sexual acts, חייב, chayav, you still have to bring a
קרבן korban שכן נהנה sheken nehene because you actually derived benefit. However,
I'll get back to that. המתעסק בשבת פטור hamis'asek beShabbos patur מלאכת
מחשבת אסרה תורה. meleches machsheves asra Torah. If you are incidentally doing
a sin on שבת, Shabbos, then it's not even a case of
שוגג, shogeg, you don't even bring a קרבן korban because the תורה
Torah only forbids intentional acts. Okay, מלאכת מחשבת. meleches machsheves. Now what
is המתעסק? hamis'asek? המתעסק בעריות, hamis'asek be'arayos, right. המתעסק בעריות hamis'asek be'arayos
is hard to imagine because you know you could do המתעסק בעריות
hamis'asek be'arayos is a person man could think let's say he's having
sex with his wife and it winds up he's having sex with
his sister or something like that. But that's not המתעסק, hamis'asek, you
were trying to have an act of intercourse, it was just with
a different person. It's sort of like trying to eat you know
you're trying you know trying to do eat one piece of food
and eating a different piece of food or whatever. So it's hard
exactly to imagine the context of המתעסק בעריות, hamis'asek be'arayos, okay, let's
not go there right now but the basic point is that why
is why is forbidden foods and forbidden sexual acts different? Because the
basic concept of המתעסק hamis'asek is that the act doesn't even relate
to you. Like if I imagine I was trying to shake your
hand and accidentally my hand turned on a light switch. Would you
say oh I turned on the light switch incidental accidentally? Or would
you say it's not even like I turned it on. It's like
I shook your hand and by accident the light went on, right?
I don't even like I wouldn't I would use passive language. I
wouldn't say I turned the light on by accident, I mean I
might. But okay, but you could understand in that case saying like
no I was I shook your hand and accidentally the light went
on. So when it's so incidental and so different from the act
you were trying to do, it is seen as not relating to
you. That's one way of understanding המתעסק hamis'asek why you don't bring
a קרבן. korban. However, when you directly your body gets benefit from
the experience, okay, it was an act of sex or an act
of eating forbidden food, you can't say oh you didn't eat that
fat, the fat got eaten. Okay, the bottom line of the reality
is is that you derived that benefit that doesn't allow you to
free yourself from the association with that act. That's how it's normally
understood. There's other ways of understanding it as well, that the act
is fundamentally an act of הנאה hana'ah not an act of eating.
But anyway, this is the basic principle. So המתעסק hamis'asek by חלבים
ועריות chalavim ve'arayos you bring a קרבן, korban, by שבת Shabbos and
other עבירות aveiros you don't. So let's I want to go back
and say one more thing about them in a minute, but let's
just finish the train of thought. So it says why don't we
say that the context of multiple קרבנות korbanos versus one קרבן korban
is שבת Shabbos versus עבודה זרה avoda zara and the contrast of
when you're
מתעסק mis'asek that by שבת Shabbos you don't bring a sin offering
and by other things you do, really not all other things, but
by forbidden foods and forbidden sexual acts you do, that's contrasting שבת
Shabbos not to עבודה זרה avoda zara but contrasting שבת Shabbos to
other to other עבירות. aveiros. Okay? So the ברייתא braisa can work,
the beginning will be עבודה זרה, avoda zara, the end will be
about other עבירות, aveiros, about like fats. And the גמרא Gemara says
like this, רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, Rabi Yochanan leta'ameih, the reason רבי יוחנן
Rabi Yochanan did not want to say that is he goes according
to his reasoning, דלא מוקי מתניתין רישא בחד טעמא וסיפא בחד טעמא.
delo moki masnisin reisha bechad ta'ama vesifa bechad ta'ama. When he has
a problematic משנה Mishna or ברייתא, braisa, he does not want to
say to resolve it by saying the first part of it is
talking about a certain circumstances and the end by a different set
of circumstances. Okay, and therefore, yes, he could resolve it the beginning
is talking about עבודה זרה avoda zara the end about other things,
about like fats, but he doesn't want to say that. That's not
for him an acceptable resolution of a problematic משנה. Mishna. דאמר רבי
יוחנן de'amar Rabi Yochanan because רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan said מאן דמתרגם
לי חבית אליבא דחד תנא. man demarsigem li chavis aliba dechad tanna.
Okay, there's a משנה Mishna in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that's complicated
and I don't even want to go into it, but the גמרא
Gemara there says the beginning doesn't work with the end and it
says well you could resolve it if you said the beginning was
by who had a was supposed to be watching a barrel and
he picked up the barrel without permission and he put it back
and something happened to the barrel. Anyway, and the way to resolve
the problem of the משנה Mishna is to say that in the
first case he put it back into the same location he took
it from and in the second case he put it. into a
different location, and that would have resolved the problem to have explained
the beginning and the end under different sets of circumstances. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan refused to accept that resolution. And he said, "No,
I'm sorry, the משנה Mishna is still a problem, that is not
an acceptable resolution." And then he said, "I'm so bothered by this
משנה Mishna that מאן דמתרגם לי חבית אליבא דחד תנא, man dematergem
lei chovis aliba dechad tanna, if you can make this משנה Mishna
of the barrel make sense according to one תנא Tanna and in
one set of circumstances,
מובילנא מאני בתריה לבי מסותא, movilna manei batrei levei masusa, I will
carry your clothes after you and accompany you to the bathhouse. I
will be such a show of gratitude." So the bottom line though
is that it's not accepted- the answer is, "Well, you can make
it work like one תנא, Tanna, just say the beginning and the
end are talking about different cases." רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan does not
accept that as an acceptable answer. So the ברייתא Braita can- this
ברייתא Braita we quoted can work if the beginning was עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and the end was other עבירות, Aveirot, but רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said to the guy, "Go teach that ברייתא Braita somewhere
else," because that's not an acceptable answer. Okay, so that was very
complicated. Now, I want to just say one very brief thing about
the other exception in שבת Shabbos to חלבים ועריות. chalavim ve-arayot. What
I just said a minute ago was, it's really not שבת Shabbos
is the exception, it's really forbidden fats and forbidden sexual acts are
the exception that you don't say מתעסק mitasek by them. But there-
it's interesting because the גמרא Gemara could have said ways in which
שבת Shabbos is the exception. I'll just give you one example. Because
of the phrase of מלאכת מחשבת, melechet machshevet, right, the גמרא Gemara
says there are two exceptional points: חלבים ועריות chalavim ve-arayot as one
exception, and then it uses this phrase מלאכת מחשבת, melechet machshevet, intentional
act by שבת, Shabbos, which seems to signal that שבת Shabbos is
an exception. So there are ways in which שבת Shabbos is an
exception. Let me tell- let me give you just a simple example.
Let's say by sha- let's say by other things. Here's one piece
of forbidden fat, and here's another piece. And we're like- not say-
let's not say forbidden fat because we said that that's an exception.
I don't know. Here's like,
you know, one נזיר, nazir, two נזירים nezirim come to me, I'm
a barber for a haircut, okay? And I am intending to give
the haircut to this נזיר, nazir, and accidentally I got distracted and
I was giving the haircut to the other נזיר. nazir. I'm still
חייב. chayav. I mean, okay, that's not a קרבן korban because it's
only a לאו. lav. Well, no, there's also an איסור issur to
do it, whatever. Okay, let's just bracket that. It doesn't matter! Okay,
I tried to do an עבירה, aveira, I did an עבירה, aveira,
it doesn't matter that I did it on slightly the wrong object,
okay? But by שבת, Shabbos, if I try to pick this apple
from a tree and accidentally I pick the other apple from a
tree, there are many cases that I'm exempt, which is crazy! I
tried to be מחלל שבת, mechallel shabbos, but because it was a
slightly different thing than I was intending, the rule of מלאכת מחשבת
melechet machshevet says that I only have to bring a קרבן korban
under extremely narrow circumstances, when it's exactly what I was intending to
do. So it's a little bit funny that the גמרא Gemara earlier
made the case of forbidden fats the exception to the rule; it
really should have made שבת Shabbos the exception, because שבת Shabbos you
could try to do עבירה aveira A, חילול שבת chillul shabbos A,
and do חילול שבת chillul shabbos A prime, right, and still be
exempt, where you would never say that by other things. Anyways, that's
just ex- that's just the end of that point.
Why don't we say that?
I don't know why the גמרא Gemara did not go there. I
mean, we do say it להלכה, le-halakha, I don't know why the
גמרא Gemara didn't go there. Okay, גופא, gufa, now we can- oy,
it would have been nice if we would have finished that yesterday.
All right, but moving on. אמר רב אמי, amar rav ami, back
to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Here's רב אמי's rav ami teaching. זבח
וקטר ונסך בהעלם אחד, ziveiach ve-kiter ve-niseich be-helem echad, you did these
three things, right, slaughtering, burning on the altar, and making a libation
in one state of forgetfulness, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav ela
achat. It's only one. Now before, רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan didn't like
that. He said there's חילוק עבודות. chiluk avodot. But here the גמרא
gemara is going to deal with it as a serious position.
אמר אביי, amar abaye, says אביי, abaye, מאי טעמא דרב אמי, mai
ta'ama de-rav ami, what's רב אמי's rav ami reason? דאמר קרא, de-amar
krah, for the verse says,
לא תעבדם, lo ta'ovdeim, it says right, "do not worship them," לא
תשתחוה להם ולא תעבדם. lo tishtachaveh lahem ve-lo ta'ovdeim.
So the הכתוב עשאן כולן עבודה אחת. hakatuv asan kulan avodah achat.
It made all of the עבודות, avodot, it put it under one
generic term, don't be עובד over them as one.
Well, ah, so how about לא תשתחוה? lo tishtachaveh? So we'll get
to לא תשתחוה lo tishtachaveh in a minute. But notice this list
did not include השתחוה. hishtachavah. This list only included the other three.
So the other three are all categorized under one word of לא
תעבדם, lo ta'ovdeim, okay? Of course, the question is, you could say
by שבת shabbos it says לא תעשה כל מלאכה. lo ta'aseh kol
melakha. All right, fine, I don't know if there's an exact answer
to that, but moving on. Okay, הכתוב עשאן כולן עבודה אחת. hakatuv
asan kulan avodah achat. ומי אמר אביי הכי, u-mi amar abaye hachi,
did אביי abaye really say that? ואמר אביי שלש השתחואות בעבודת כוכבים,
ve-amar abaye shalosh hishtachava'ot be-avodat kochavim, it says לא תשתחוה lo tishtachaveh
three times by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רש״י rashi quotes
it: כי לא תשתחוה לאל אחר, ki lo tishtachaveh le-el acher, לא
תשתחוה לאלהיהם, lo tishtachaveh le-eloheihem, and what's the third one? לא תשתחוה
להם ולא תעבדם, lo tishtachaveh lahem ve-lo ta'ovdeim, okay, three times. So
why does it say three times not to bow down to עבודה
זרה? avodah zarah? למה? lama? אחת לכדרכה, achat le-ke-darkah, one is when
it's the natural thing to do for that עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
the normal thing, okay? ואחת שלא כדרכה, ve-achat she-lo ke-darkah, even when
the עבודה זרה avodah zarah is not normally worshipped that way, right,
we say- we say bow down is one of those four things.
that even if it's not the normal way of doing it, and
how about the third one? ואחת לחלק, v'achat l'chaleik, to say that
every עבודה avoda is a separate act and therefore a separate קרבן.
korban. And here he's explaining רבי אמי Rabbi Ami to say the
three things are all one קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ודרבי אמי קאמר וליה לא סבירא ליה, u'd'Rabbi Ami ka'amar v'lei lo
sevira lei, oh, he's going according to רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, but
he himself doesn't hold of it. Now I just want to pause
for one second to go to what Michael was saying, or whatever,
why here does the גמרא Gemara accept the idea that it's all
one קרבן, korban, but the גמרא Gemara at the beginning of yesterday
basically completely rejected the possibility that it would just be one קרבן?
korban? So תוספות Tosafot says the difference is that this list did
not contain the word השתחוה. hishtachava. Okay, you could say לא תשתחוה,
lo tishtachaveh, everybody, what תוספות Tosafot says is basically the גמרא Gemara
feels השתחוה hishtachava because it's said separate has to be singling itself
out. So you could say that in one of two ways. You
could say all three are one קרבן korban and השתחוה hishtachava is
a different one, that it's singling itself out, or you could say
because it singled itself out, it made every single act a separate
קרבן. korban. Okay, so it would be four קרבנות. korbanot. But so
you could say so what רבי אמי Rabbi Ami is saying is
the three that are not השתחוה hishtachava is one קרבן korban and
השתחוה hishtachava is one קרבן. korban. That's fine. השתחוה hishtachava is at
least a separate thing. Okay, the problem was yesterday the position of
רבי זכאי Rabbi Zakai was saying all four are one קרבן. korban.
That's not an acceptable position. Okay, so those are the positions here,
either all four are four קרבנות korbanot or if you do all
four you bring two קרבנות, korbanot, one for the three for the
ones that are classic עבודות avodot in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and one for השתחוה. hishtachava. That would be what רבי אמי Rabbi
Ami is saying. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
And by the way, as I mentioned the other day, the הירושלמי
Yerushalmi says that you would bring also a third קרבן korban if
you did עבודה כדרכה. avoda k'darkah. You bring one קרבן korban for
the three עבודות avodot that are the עבודות avodot in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash regardless of whether it's כדרכה, k'darkah, one קרבן korban
for השתחוה, hishtachava, and one קרבן korban for the עבודה avoda that
is distinctive to that עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay, so each one
is a different genre of
transgression. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומי אמר,
u'mi amar, I just did that. Okay, גופא, gufa, let's go back
to אביי's Abaye statement. אמר אביי שלש השתחוות בעבודת כוכבים, Amar Abaye
shalosh hishtachavot b'avodat kochavim, it says three times. Okay, למה לי אחת
כדרכה ואחת שלא כדרכה ואחת לחלק? lama li achat k'darkah v'achat shelo
k'darkah v'achat l'chaleik? So the גמרא Gemara says, לכדרכה, l'k'darkah, now why
do you need to say don't bow down when it's the natural
thing to do? איכה יעבדו הגוים האלה נפקא, eicha ya'avdu hagoyim ha'eleh
nafka, we
that's the general rule that every עבודה זרה avoda zara you're חייב
chayav for its sort of distinctive form of worship. So if it's
distinctive to bow down, I mean if that is the natural way
that its followers worship it, that's covered in the verse of "how
do those pagans worship their gods?" That covers every form of worship
that is classic for that god. So why do you need a
פסוק pasuk by bowing down? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, ella,
you're right, you don't. אחת כדרכה ושלא כדרכה, achat k'darkah v'shelo k'darkah,
when we said one is needed for when it's the normal way
of doing it, we don't mean normal normal. We mean somewhat normal,
okay, which means this עבודה זרה, avoda zara, most of its worshippers
will not bow down to it. If you bow down though, they
won't say you're crazy. They'll say, okay, that was an acceptable thing
but it's not what we normally do around here. All right, so
that's that case. Exactly.
That's as opposed to שלא כדרכה shelo k'darkah completely. You go to
פעור Peor and you bow down, they say get the heck out
of here. Okay, פעור Peor we do in a very different way.
This is a god that we worship by doing disgusting things, not
that we do honorable things. Okay, so there's different degrees of שלא
כדרכה. shelo k'darkah. All right, but a classic כדרכה k'darkah we already
know from that generic category of כדרכה. k'darkah. Okay, so one is
the כדרכה ושלא כדרכה, k'darkah v'shelo k'darkah, ואחת לשלא כדרכה, v'achat l'shelo
k'darkah, one's fully
שלא כדרכה, shelo k'darkah, ואחת לחלק, v'achat l'chaleik, and one to tell
you that each one is a separate קרבן. korban. Okay, now we
move on, now we've covered the issues about classic forms of worship,
the four, bowing down, is that distinct? Now we get to this
very, like I'd say historically extremely important line in the המשנה, Mishnah,
which includes in עבודה זרה avoda zara one who accepts this as
a god upon them, okay, מקבלו עליו באלוה, mekablo alav b'elo'ah, והאומר
לו אלי אתה, v'ha'omer lo eli ata, you are my god. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. The גמרא, Gemara,
which is fascinating, right, we needed a פסוק pasuk to show you
these four, we need a פסוק pasuk to bowing down, we need
a פסוק pasuk for כדרכה. k'darkah. This idea that when a person
says to this idol, "You are my god," that that is an
act of עבודה זרה avoda zara that you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
the גמרא Gemara quotes absolutely no פסוק pasuk and no basis to
tell me how we know. Haven't done any physical act. The גמרא
Gemara has no פסוק pasuk to say how we know that that's
an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara and that you're חייב. chayav.
I'm going to let that sit with you for a little bit
and then I'm going to go back and say something about it.
But let's see what the גמרא Gemara does say about this. Okay,
אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב כיון שאמר לו
אלי אתה חייב, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav
keivan she'amar lo eli ata chayav, as soon as a person said
to this idol, "You are my
god," חייב, chayav, you transgressed. For? Now for what purposes? אי לקטלא,
I le-ktala, if to say you're deserving of execution, מתניתין היא, matnitin
hi, of course, that's our משנה. mishna. Again, how do we- our
משנה mishna knows that, we're not saying. But that's our משנה. mishna.
אלא, Ela, so what are you telling us that's not in our
משנה? mishna? לקרבן, Le-korban, that if you do it and you somehow
were שוגג, shogeg, you didn't think it was forbidden, you bring a
קרבן, korban, okay, for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now why should that
be different? Okay,
ואפילו לרבנן, ve-afilu le-rabbanan, here's an interesting thing. It is easier sometimes
to get the death penalty than it is to bring a קרבן.
korban. Okay, for the death penalty, you can get a death penalty
for an act that does not involve a physical act. Like a
classic example we're about to see is somebody who blasphemes God. It's
only a verbal act. That's seen different as a physical act, okay,
and you get the death penalty. But for a קרבן, korban, the
basic principle is by a קרבן korban the פסוק pasuk says ועשה
מאחת מהנה, ve-asah me-achat me-henna, actually this is a פסוק pasuk we
brought yesterday or there's other times where it says עשה asah and
we say a קרבן korban you only bring if it's a physical
act. So now we've got a problem. Tell me you get the
death penalty for verbally accepting a god, okay, that's עבודה זרה avoda
zara fine, but to tell me you get a קרבן, korban, whoa,
one minute, there's no act. Okay, it's a fascinating idea that you
would need some more of an act to bring a קרבן. korban.
Okay, anyway, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ואפילו לרבנן, ve-afilu le-rabbanan,
even according to the rabbis that normally say that for a קרבן
korban you need an act. What is this issue? ואפילו לרבנן, ve-afilu
le-rabbanan, excuse me, the גמרא Gemara says, even according to the רבנן?
rabbanan? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. אינו חייב אלא
דבר שיש בו מעשה. Eino chayav ela davar she-yesh bo ma'aseh. You
only have to bring a קרבן korban for עבודה זרה avoda zara
if there's an act associated with it. כגון, Kegon, for example, זביחה
וקיטור וניסוך והשתחויה, zivvach ve-kitor ve-nisuch ve-hishtachava, like,
you know, all those things and bowing down. ואמר ריש לקיש, Ve-amar
Reish Lakish, now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said that seems fine, but
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said מאן תנא השתחויה? man tanna hishtachava? One
minute, since when is bowing down an act? You're just moving your
body. You're not sort of like interacting with anything else. So the
גמרא Gemara here assumes that a speech act and an act of
bowing down are the same category of minimal acts. All right, you
could distinguish between them and I'll get to that in a minute,
but the גמרא Gemara assumes that they are in the same category
of minimal acts. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says wait, השתחויה hishtachava
doesn't belong in that list. Who says השתחויה hishtachava is considered a
significant act to bring a קרבן? korban? רבי עקיבא היא, Rabbi Akiva
hi, it's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאמר לא בעינן מעשה. De-amar lo
ba'inan ma'aseh. You don't need a real act. Okay, why do we
know? Because there's a debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the
רבנן rabbanan about a מגדף, megadef, somebody that curses God, בשוגג be-shogeg
do you bring a קרבן? korban? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I
consider speech an act and you bring a קרבן, korban, and the
רבנן rabbanan say it's not an act. And אביי Abaye here assumes
that bowing down is the same degree of a minimal act like
speech. Okay, so that's the debate. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva minimal act
is enough for a קרבן korban and for the רבנן rabbanan no.
אקיצור, A-kitzur, so here, how could you say that if somebody does
an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara
verbally accepts this god as a god that they bring a קרבן?
korban? That only works according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says small acts is enough. The rabbis don't say it.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, כי קאמר רב נמי לרבי עקיבא
קאמר. ki ka'amar Rav nami le-Rabbi Akiva ka'amar. Fine, he would say
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the verbal acceptance of עבודה זרה
avoda zara brings a קרבן korban according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that says verbal act, small act is enough for a קרבן. korban.
So the גמרא Gemara says לרבי עקיבא פשיטא. le-Rabbi Akiva peshita. So
that's no חידוש. chiddush. Of course, היינו מגדף. hainu megadef. That's no
different than מגדף. megadef. If מגדף megadef is a verbal act, blaspheming
God, and you bring a קרבן, korban, so verbally accepting עבודה זרה
avoda zara is an act and you bring a קרבן. korban. Within
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there's no חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, מהו דתימא אימא, ma de-teima eima, it thought עד כאן
לא מחייב רבי עקיבא קרבן אלא במגדף. ad kan lo mechayeiv Rabbi
Akiva korban ella be-megadef. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva only says by מגדף
megadef the verbal act makes you bring a קרבן. korban. דכתיב ביה,
De-chtiv beih, it says regarding it כרת. karet. By מגדף megadef it
says explicitly, right, ונוקב שם השם מות יומת, ve-nokev shem Hashem mot
yummat, איש
איש כי יקלל אלוהיו ונשא חטאו. ish ish ki yekalel elohav venasa
cheto. So it says כרת. karet. And normally those go together, you
don't bring a קרבן korban except on something that's punishable by כרת.
karet. So since it explicitly labels it for כרת, karet, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says I'm more inclined to see that you'll be obligated
in a קרבן. korban. All right, so there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say you'd get a קרבן korban even though it's just verbal.
אבל הכא, Aval hacha, by
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, דלא כתיב ביה כרת. de-lo chtiv beih karet.
Sure you get the death penalty, but it never says you get
כרת. karet. And כרת karet is normally the flip side of קרבן,
korban, so there I'm not as inclined to think you should bring
a קרבן. korban. אימא לא, Eima lo, maybe even רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva would say you don't bring a קרבן korban by עבודה זרה
avoda zara by the verbal acceptance of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. קמשמע
לן דהיקשא היקש. Kamashma lan de-hekkesha hikkesh. It teaches you know that
all acts of עבודה זרה avoda zara are linked to one another
and you do bring a קרבן korban by עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
at least according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even by just the
verbal act. Okay, where do you have
they linked? דכתיב וישתחוו לו ויזבחו לו, de-chtiv vayishtachavu lo vayizbechu lo,
they bowed down to it and they sacrificed to it, this is
the calf, the golden calf, ויאמרו אלה אלוהיך ישראל, vayomru eileh elohecha
Yisrael, these are your gods Israel אשר העלוך מארץ מצרים. asher he'elucha
me-eretz Mitzrayim. Okay, so therefore it links all three: slaughtering, bowing down.
and verbal acceptance. So since by slaughtering is a clearly an act
and you bring a קרבן, korban, the same is true by bowing
down and the same is true by verbal acceptance. At least we're
not making the argument according to the רבנן, Rabanan, but at least
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's enough of an act to
bring a קרבן. korban. Now one minute. I want to say two
things about this. Okay, so basically what the גמרא Gemara said is
for those that say that speech is, you know, it's sort of
it's a debate whether speech is enough of an act to bring
a קרבן, korban, and is bowing down enough of an act to
bring a קרבן, korban, that is considered the same as speech. If
speech is enough then bowing down is, if speech is not it's
not. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi suggests a distinction, that speech could not be
an act but bowing down could be an act. Now one point
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, "What's the difference? Speech you move your lips
a little bit, bowing down you bend yourself a little bit. Like
how do we measure? I mean what's, you know, where's why isn't
speech or say it the other way,
why isn't it obvious that speech is an act? Speech you're moving
your lips, since when is moving your lips different than moving any
other part of your body?" So the answer seems, although the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi never answers it directly, the answer seems that the difference is
is that the significance of speech is not the physical act, right?
The significance of speech is not that the lips sort of you
know the body part actually interacted with some part of the physical
universe and effected some physical change, right? It's actually it allowed you
to express a thought, right, which is a mental reality. It allowed
you to express a mental reality through the moving of your lips,
but it was that expression of that thought that is what is
the act of speech. And that's why speech really could be seen
as much more of a mental act that is expressed outwards than
a physical act, which raises an interesting question about bowing down, because
bowing down really is a little bit between those two. By bowing
down you're not interacting with the physical world outside of yourself, you're
not effecting some physical change on something else, but you are expressing,
you are expressing something, right? So how about right hand motions, right?
Let's say we said speech wasn't an act. What if somebody signed,
would that be an act? Okay, so actually it does make sense.
It's not about the degree of movement, but it's to what degree
is it about the physical reality of that act or to what
degree is it about that act expressing something that is you know
non-physical, communicating. All right, so anyway, that is a fascinating question and
but the and then the so A is speech different than other
acts as physical act and where do you put bowing down with
speech or on the other side of it. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara here puts the two together and says that that would be
the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the רבנן. Rabanan. Yes,
חנניה.
Chananiah. Just a question for this?
If yes, but you get a death penalty even for things that
are not act based, that don't have to satisfy the same definition
of an act.
Right. So why would you also have to bring a קרבן? korban?
No, קרבן korban is in a case when you didn't, weren't intentional,
when you thought it was permissible or something like that. You can't,
no, you wouldn't have both. When we speak about קרבן, korban, we're
talking about a scenario where you think it's permissible. Yeah, Michael.
So when the fact that we're learning all these הלכות halachos about
עבודה זרה avodah zarah from the עגל, egel, wouldn't that be a
very big challenge to the premise that it wasn't really עבודה זרה?
avodah zarah? Well, yes and no because Michael raises an important point
and maybe this is a good place to say it. There's two
aspects of עבודה זרה avodah zarah and actually this will tie into
another point I wanted to make. Okay, there's עבודה זרה avodah zarah
which is accepting this thing as another god, okay, that's what we
classically call לא יהיה לך אלהים אחרים על פני. lo yihye lecha
elohim acheirim al panai. Some people say that's what they did by
the עגל, egel, actually we're about to get to a discussion in
the גמרא Gemara about that, did they believe that the עגל egel
was some competing god with God or some different god. But then
for the רמב"ן, Ramban, the רמב"ן Ramban says you can do עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, I mean it's actually in the פסוקים, pesukim, right?
The פסוקים pesukim say לא תעשון כל תמונה ביום דבר השם, lo
saasun kol tmuna biyom dibber Hashem, you didn't see any image when
God spoke to you, don't make an image. It's not talking about
the worship of other gods, it's talking about the worship of God
through an
image, okay, which is clearly the עגל egel is either accepting the
עגל egel as a different god or the worship of God through
an image. Either one is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, and that's
important to know, and both are an act of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah that's חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So it really doesn't matter whether
you believe in this as a god or whether you believe you're
worshipping God through this image, either thing is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay, but אבא יורה, Abba Yoreh, we did say that according to
רבא Rava that you're not believing in it.
What? Yeah, but that doesn't but that is not a worship of
a god through an image, that's not even a worship of a
god. Okay, it's not the, whatever, think it through. Okay, you need
there to be a worship of a god that's going on here,
whether it's God or some other god. Anyway, but now I want
to make a very important point because I told you that I
asked you, since when is saying, "You are my god," an act
of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? It may be a violation of לא
יהיה לך אלהים אחרים על פני, lo yihye lecha elohim acheirim al
panai, you're believing in other gods, but you're not worshipping other gods.
How do we know that you're חייב מיתה? chayav misah? The גמרא
Gemara never tells us how we know you're חייב מיתה. chayav misah.
So there's an interesting debate here basically between תוספות Tosafos and רמב"ן.
Ramban. תוספות Tosafos says way back at the משנה, Mishna, he says
based on the fact that this פסוק pasuk just linked it, like
וישתחוו לו ויזבחו לו. Vayishtachavu lo vayizbechu lo. ויזבחו לו ויאמרו אלה
אלוהיך ישראל, vayizbachu lo vayomru eileh elohecha Yisrael,
that what it's saying is that saying אלה אלוהיך, eileh elohecha, saying
this, right? אלי אתה, Eili ata, you are my God. He says
that that is the most basic form of worship. Every, every religion,
every God is a basic form of worship. And we're going to
say the four classic things, right? Slaughtering, bowing down, and libation. The
most basic, it's not a step prior to worship. First you believe
in it and then you worship. The verb—meaning it's you're thinking about
it in your head, that's a maybe a transgression of לא יהיה
לך lo yihyeh lecha without an עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But the
act of verbally making a statement, "you are my God", that is
the most basic form of עבודה avoda for all עבודה avoda for
all Gods, okay? And that's learned from this פסוק pasuk that links
the three.
What? How long does he go? Well, the verbal act.
You need the verbal act. So for תוספות, Tosfos, we learned the
idea that it's an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara from the
פסוק pasuk אלה אלוהיך ישראל. eileh elohecha Yisrael. רמב"ן Ramban says, it's
gonna sound like the same, but it's actually like conceptually it's the
flip. רמב"ן Ramban says, you know, what's the prohibition for example of
worshipping עבודה זרה avoda zara and bowing down to עבודה זרה? avoda
zara? Based on everything we've learned, we would say it's לא תשתחוה
להם ולא תעבדם. lo tishtachaveh lahem velo ta'avdem. רמב"ן Ramban says no,
that's not the prohibition. The prohibition for worshipping עבודה זרה avoda zara
is לא יהיה לך אלוהים אחרים על פני. lo yihyeh lecha elohim
acheirim al panai. So for the רמב"ן, Ramban, the prohibition of worshipping
עבודה זרה avoda zara is fundamentally prohibited because it's an expression of
your belief of accepting this other God as your God. Okay? But
the fundamental prohibition of עבודה זרה avoda zara is not the act
of worship, it is the act of accepting this other God as
your God. So for the רמב"ן, Ramban, of course if you say
אלי אתה, Eili ata, you're חייב chayav for עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
The fundamental point of עבודה זרה avoda zara is לא יהיה לך
אלוהים אחרים. lo yihyeh lecha elohim acheirim. You don't need a פסוק
pasuk to teach you that. That is the act of accepting another
God. The חידוש chiddush is that even when you slaughter and do
all those other things, that's also seen interpreted because that's what the
context means. Okay? Certainly works for רבא. Rava. The אבנא יירא avana
yeira doesn't work. I don't know what you would say according to
אביי. Abaye. But anyway, according to רבא, Rava, the whole point is
you're חייב chayav because you are accepting another God. So a very
different way, right? רמב"ן Ramban says all עבודה זרה avoda zara acts
of worship, their basic transgression is accepting another God and therefore it
starts with אלי אתה. Eili ata. And תוספות Tosfos says no, עבודה
זרה avoda zara that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa for is an
act of worship. It just so happens that אלי אתה Eili ata
is the fundamental act of worship. Okay. Interesting going back to Michael's
question. According to the רמב"ן, Ramban, if somebody worshipped a God through
an image, would they be, would they, maybe, I mean that's prohibited,
but maybe they're not חייב מיתה, chayav misa, right? Maybe the חיוב
מיתה chiyuv misa is only in the context of a worship of
a foreign God. רמב"ם Rambam thinks it's all the same, but רמב"ן
Ramban says no no no, it's very much all about accepting another
God. Okay? So all that really important theological discussion is not in
the גמרא Gemara at all. Yes.
How would the people who worshiped the golden calf be able to
be forgiven for the golden calf, right? Then why could they not
in the future, if that's ideology, right? Why shouldn't there be a
ability to receive forgiveness?
Who said you can't receive forgiveness for idolatry? You can, all sins
you can be forgiven for if you do תשובה. teshuva.
Oh, you wouldn't get the death penalty. Oh, you would, sure!
You would be forgiven and get the death penalty.
Forgiveness is not, forgiveness of God is not what the courts do.
Okay? It's not for the courts to judge whether you are truly
repentant or not. The courts do not waive punishments because you're repentant.
The courts administer justice. Okay? Repentance is for God to forgive you.
All right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Now a little אגדתא. agaddata. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Yochanan, אלמלא
ו' שבהעלוך, ilmala vav shebe'heelucha,
"these are the Gods that raised you up out of Egypt", it's
in the plural, נתחייבו רשעים שבישראל כליה, nitchayvu resha'im shebeYisrael kelaya,
we would have been deserving of complete destruction. Because even at the
time where we worshipped the calf, we didn't exclude God. These are
the Gods, God plus the calf. So we weren't excluding God. If
we had just said "this is the God that took you out",
not only would it have been a worship of עבודה זרה avoda
zara but a complete rejection of God, then we would have never
survived, we would have been totally wiped out. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, כתנאי. katannai. That's not so clear. That's a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. Okay? אחרים אומרים, Acheirim omrim, others say, אלמלא
ו' שבהעלוך נתחייבו רשעים שבישראל כליה, ilmala vav shebe'heelucha nitchayvu resha'im shebeYisrael
kelaya, what we just said. Were it not for that ו' vav
we would have been deserving of complete destruction. אמר לו רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי, Amar lo Rabi Shimon ben Yochai, רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
Rabi Shimon ben Yochai said, והלא כל המשתף שם שמיים ודבר אחר
נעקר מן העולם. vahalo kol hamishtatef shem shamayim vedavar acher ne'ekar min
ha'olam. You can't say that. Anybody that combines God's name, God with
something else, is, that is deserving to be destroyed. So if we
said "these are the Gods", the calf plus God, that would have
been deserving of being completely destroyed. So that's not what's going on
there. Okay. That's not what saved us, that actually is just as
problematic. So, אלא מה תלמוד לומר אשר העלוך? ella ma talmud lomar
asher heelucha? So what does it mean אשר העלוך asher heelucha in
the plural? שאיוו אלוהות הרבה. she'ivu elohut harbeh.
They yearned for many Gods. Okay. Yes, it doesn't mean just the
עגל, Egel, it shows that they wanted many gods. So okay, so
it's still just as bad. So the simple read of this sounds
like it's better to abandon God and accept other gods than to
equate God with other gods and put God in the same category.
That's the simple implication of Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai saying what sounds
a little bizarre, but maybe at some level you could understand it,
you know, it's like when you bring God down and just make
God like the other gods, one thing to worship a different god
and put God aside, but to put them on the same category,
maybe that's worse. Maharsha does not like that at all. He says,
how could it be worse to combine God with other gods than
to completely reject God, right? There's no way combining is worse. So
what the Ramban tries to say is is that in this context
when it says many gods, it means a belief that yes, God
is still the supreme God, but אשר העלוך, Asher he'elukha, they wanted
to worship the lower gods, okay, and that is at least better.
They're not forgetting about God, they're still thinking of God as the
supreme, but they're focusing their worship on lower gods. And that's why
they weren't deserving of destruction. But had they completely abandoned
God—
No, they weren't, they got saved. Right, but the point is had
they done it in a worse way, they would have been wiped
out. So the first opinion was, had they said this is the
god and put God aside, they would have been wiped out. The
second position said, no, if they would have combined God with the
עגל Egel they also would have been wiped out. Okay, that's just
as bad. They wouldn't have survived that. The reason they survived, says
the Maharsha, is because they kept God up there, this is the
way the Maharsha reads it, okay, to make more sense of it.
God is still distinct and supreme and we're just going to worship
all the lower gods. That they were able to be forgiven for.
But had they completely pushed God aside or had they equated God
with the other gods, that they wouldn't have survived. That's the way
the Maharsha reads the second answer. Although the simple sense of the
second answer is even more extreme.
They still kept God supreme and wanted other lower—
He just reads that into it in order to make sense out
of it. Okay, but the simple sense is better to not bring
God down with the other, better to like put God completely aside
than to combine God with the other gods. That's at least the
way the simple reading of what's going on here. By the way,
this issue of משתתף שם שמים ודבר אחר, Mishtatef Shem Shamayim Vedavar
Acher, you know what, I'm actually going to hold on to it,
we'll get to it when we get to the עמוד ב. Amud
Bet. Let's keep on going.
Okay, אבל המגפף והמנשק והמכבד ומכבד ומרביץ, Aval hamagafef ve-hamenashek ve-hamikhabed u-mikhabed
u-marbitz, all these other acts of honor and respect and adoration, if
it's not in a context of, what do you call it,
if it's not a classic form of worship, you do not—it's a
simple negative prohibition, but it's not punishable by death. Okay, כי אתו
אבדימי אמר רבי אלעזר, Ki atu Avdimi amar Rabbi Elazar, when Avdimi
came from Eretz Yisrael he said in the name of Rabbi Elazar,
אכולם לוקה, A-kulam loke, on all these things, these acts of adoration
or whatever you get lashes, חוץ מהנודר בשמו והמקיים בשמו. Chutz mehanoder
bishmo ve-hakayam bishmo. The end of the Mishna says somebody who takes
a vow in the name of another god or an oath in
the name of another god
also transgresses. So he says, oh, for the vow and the oath
you don't get lashes, for these acts of adoration you do. Okay,
so what's the reason? So the Gemara says like this: מאי שנא
הנודר בשמו והמקיים בשמו דלא לקי? Mai shna hanoder bishmo ve-hakayam bishmo
dela laki? Why do you not get lashes over there when you
take a vow? משום דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה, Mishum de-havei lav
she-ein bo ma'aseh, because it's without an act, it's verbal. We're back
to that. So no lashes if something is only verbal. Okay, so
the Gemara says, הני נמי? Hanei nami? So these other acts of
worship that are not true, that are not avodah zarah per se,
so you also shouldn't get lashes. Not because they're not physical acts,
but for a different reason.
משום דהוי לאו שבכללות. Mishum de-havei lav she-bikhallalut. It's a generic lav.
What makes it a generic? Because it just says like, you know,
לא תעבדם. Lo ta'ovdem. So the point is so what? So לא
תעבדם Lo ta'ovdem means avodah contains a lot of different acts of
avodah. Why does that make it generic? I mean, you know, how
about the one that says don't do melacha on Shabbat, לא תעשה
כל מלאכה? Lo ta'aseh kol melacha? Why is that not a generic
type of a thing, right? כל מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו Kol melekhet
avodah lo ta'asu by Yom Tov? You get lashes for melachas on
Yom Tov? Why don't we say, well that's just generic, it includes
a lot of different acts? So that's not so clear to me,
I don't really get it, but I mean Tosafot asks the same
question. If you look at Tosafot he says, אכולם
אינו לוקה, A-kulam eino loke, look at Tosafot, אפילו למאן דאמר בסוף
פרק כל שעה דלוקי נא ומבושל משום צלי אש. Afilu le-man de-amar
be-sof perek Kol Sha'ah de-loki na u-mevushal mishum tzali esh. It says
don't eat from the Korban Pesach except roasted by fire. So let's
say you ate, like let's say, okay, let's say you ate something
raw. Would you get lashes? So says, so why isn't that just
generic, anything not roasted by fire includes a lot of different things?
We don't consider that a לאו שבכללות. lav she-bikhallalut. Okay, וזג וחרצן
משום כל אשר יעשה מגפן Ve-zag ve-chartzan mishum kol asher ye'aseh migefen
or like this thing by
Nazir. הני מפרשי יצא מכלל דלא תעבדם דלא מפרש קרא דאיירי מגפף
ומנשק. Hanei mefarshei yatza mikhlal de-lo ta'ovdem delo mefaresh kra de-ayari magafef
u-menashek. That's a little clearer. When you say not roasted, it's a
little clearer what you have in mind. So then you would get
lashes. But when you just say don't worship them in a very
generic abstract way, it's not so clear what you mean. So therefore
it's not— Too abstract and that's why you don't get lashes. That's
what תוספות Tosefot says. Okay, but then we're talking about the non-classic
forms of worship. Classic forms are seen that it's clear. לא תעבדם
lo ta'avdeim means classic. But to say לא תעבדם lo ta'avdeim means
these other acts of adoration that aren't even normal ways it's worshipped,
that's too abstract. You don't get lashes. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. He says והדר אמרינן בפרק קמא דביצה דמבשל גיד הנשה
ביום טוב לוקה חמש וחייב נמי מבשל ביום טוב. vehadar amrinan b'perek
kama d'beitzah d'mivashil gid hanasheh b'yom tov lokei chamesh v'chayeiv nami mivashil
b'yom tov. You get lashes for doing a מלאכה melachah on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. There also it's generic. It says don't do any
מלאכה. melachah. Okay. So לא חשבינן להו לאו שבכללות. lo hashvinan lehu
lav shebichlalot. We don't say that's too abstract. דכתיב כל מלאכת עבודה
לא תעשו dechesiv kol melachas avodah lo sa'asu כמו לא תעבדם. k'mo
lo ta'avdeim. Why is that different than לא תעבדם? lo ta'avdeim? It's
just a generic concept. Okay. דהכא דהאי מפרש טפי דכתיב עבודה לשמה
כל מלאכה שהיא עבודה. d'hacha d'hai mefarsh tfei dechesiv avodah lishmo kol
melachah shehi avodah.
מלאכת עבודה meleches avodah is a little more specific. It's not saying
don't do any מלאכה. melachah. It's don't do a laborious מלאכה. melachah.
מלאכת עבודה. meleches avodah.
There's an adjective there. Okay, so because it's a little more concrete
and specific, don't do laborious מלאכה, melachah, that's not so abstract. But
something like this, don't worship them, when it's not even referring to
the classic forms of worship, hugging, kissing, acts of adoration, that's too
abstract. I don't know what you're talking about don't worship them. When
it's so abstract, you don't get lashes. That's at least the גמרא's
Gemara claim. Okay, I still don't really get it but that's the
גמרא's Gemara claim. So let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. So
you shouldn't get lashes here, it's too abstract.
Okay. דאין לוקין על לאו שבכללות de'ein lokin al lav shebichlalot and
I know that you don't get lashes on an abstract prohibition. How
do I know this? דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. Baraita.
מניין לאוכל מן הבהמה קודם שתצא נפשה שהוא בלא תעשה? minayin le'ochel
min habehemah kodem shetetzai nafshah shehu belo sa'aseh? How do I know
that if a person eats the meat of an animal before the
animal expires, it was slaughtered and you grab a meat from it
and it but it's still thrashing around? How do I know you
transgress? שתלמוד לומר לא תאכלו על הדם. she'talmud lomar lo sochlu al
hadam. Don't eat over blood while the blood is still in the
animal. דבר אחר, davar acher, another thing that you can include from
this prohibition, okay. לא תאכלו על הדם לא תאכלו בשר ועדיין דם
במזרק. lo sochlu al hadam lo sochlu basar v'adayin dam bamizrak.
Don't eat the meat of sacrifices while the blood is still in
the basin, while the blood has not yet been put on the
altar. That's a completely different prohibition. רבי דוסא אומר מניין שאין מברין
על הרוגי בית דין. Rabbi Dosa omer minayin she'ein mavrin al harugei
beis din. How do you know that you don't give the mourner's
meal to mourners who have just, you know, a relative has just
been executed by the court? תלמוד לומר לא תאכלו על הדם. talmud
lomar lo sochlu al hadam. Don't eat over blood being spilled. And
here it meant when a person was executed. Completely different prohibition.
Wildly different prohibitions. רבי עקיבא אומר מניין לסנהדרין שהרגו את הנפש שאין
טועמין מכלום כל אותו היום. Rabbi Akiva omer minayin le'sanhedrin she'hargu es
hanefesh she'ein to'amin miklum kol oso hayom. Similar to the idea of
an execution, similar case of execution. How do you know when a
בית דין Beis Din has ruled that somebody is liable to death
penalty, that it's forbidden for them to eat the whole day? Right?
Because they shouldn't trivialize
what they've just done. Oh, he's חייב מיתה, chayav misah, let's go
have lunch. Okay, how do you know you can't do that? תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar the verse says לא תאכלו על הדם. lo sochlu
al hadam. Don't eat once you have ruled that somebody's blood needs
to be spilled. Okay. ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says, אזהרה לבן סורר ומורה מניין? azharah le'ben sorer u'moreh
minayin? Where do you know that a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer
u'moreh where it says you execute him, how do you know that,
where does it say it's prohibited for him to do what he
did? תלמוד לומר לא תאכלו על הדם. talmud lomar lo sochlu al
hadam. What's that have to do with blood? רש״י Rashi says don't
do a type of an eating that's going to get your blood
spilled. That we told you was liable to the death penalty. Anyway,
okay, so you have all these wildly different things included in this
verse. ואמר רבי אבין בר חייא ואיתימא רבי אבין בר כהנא, v'amar
Rabbi Avin bar Chiya v'sima Rabbi Avin bar Kahana, על כולם אינו
לוקה, al kulam eino lokei, you don't get lashes for any of
them. משום דהוי ליה לאו שבכללות mishum d'haveilei lav shebichlalot because it's
a generic לאו. lav. Now that's really generic. It includes in its
umbrella things that include in it wildly different things. But somehow we're
applying that also to an idea of לא תעבדם lo ta'avdeim which
is different forms of adoration. Okay. So anyway, so how could you
say you get lashes? It's too generic of a לאו. lav. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא elah fine, let's reverse what we said.
כי אתא רבין אמר רבי אלעזר, ki asah Ravin amar Rabbi Elazar,
let's say he said the exact opposite. על כולן אינו לוקה, al
kulan eino lokei, you don't get lashes for any of the things
in the משנה, Mishnah, hugging, kissing, all those things, חוץ chutz the
one thing you do get lashes for is מן הנשבע בשמו והמקיים
בשמו. min hanishba b'shmo v'hamekayem b'shmo. If you take an oath or
a vow. Because there the prohibition is clearer. We're going to see
in a minute that's learned from the verse שם אלהים אחרים לא
תזכירו לא ישמע על פיך. shem elohim acherim lo saszkiru lo yishama
al picha. So that's very explicit, don't use the name of another
god in some type, well we'll see what it means, certainly it
means in a religious context. Okay. So therefore that is not a
לאו שבכללות, lav shebichlalot, that's more concrete and therefore you get lashes.
How about the fact that it's verbal? It's not an action. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא הנך דלא לקי? mai shna hanoch
d'lo laki?
So why don't you get on the hugging and the kissing or
whatever? דהוי ליה לאו שבכללות, d'haveilei lav shebichlalot, it's too generic of
a prohibition. הני נמי לאו שאין בו מעשה נינהו. hani nami lav
she'ein bo ma'aseh ninhu. So swearing and taking an oath, it might
be more concrete and specific but it's still it's without an action.
No, הא כרבי יהודה. ha k'Rabbi Yehuda. This is following רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו d'amar lav she'ein
bo ma'aseh loken alav who says a לאו lav without an action
you get lashes for. There actually is an opinion, the opinion of
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that even a verbal act you do get
lashes. So we said before, a verbal act you can get the
death penalty. You can't bring a חטאת. chatat. Can you get now
lashes for a verbal act that for a not just a verbal
act for no act, okay that's a debate. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you can even if you're passive, even if it's just a
verbal act or even if you're totally passive, and the general principle
is no, to get lashes you need to do an active act.
Okay, where do you see this debate? תניא, Tanya, we saw in
a ברייתא. braisa. לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר, Lo sosiru mimenu ad
boker,
don't leave from the קרבן korban over till the next morning, and
if you leave over till the next morning, you burn it by
a fire. בא כתוב ליתן עשה אחר לא תעשה. Ba kasuv litein
asei achar lo taaseh. So it gives you a positive thing to
do if you transgress the negative. If you left it to the
next morning, burn it. לומר, Lomar, this teaches you שאין לוקין עליו.
she-ein lokin alav. Because you have the positive מצוה mitzvah to fix
it, if you left it to the next morning, here's what you
got to do, you burn it. So since the positive מצוה mitzvah
fixes the negative, you don't get lashes for transgressing the negative. דברי
רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
רבי יעקב אומר, Rabbi Yaakov omer, לא מן השם הוא זה. lo
min hasheim hu zeh. It's not because the positive one fixes it.
Even if there was no positive מצוה, mitzvah, you wouldn't get lashes.
Why? אלא משום דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה, Ela mishum de-havei lav
she-ein bo maaseh, because you're being totally passive. You're transgressing it by
not doing something. וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו, Ve-chol
lav she-ein bo maaseh ein lokin alav, and if you didn't do
an act, you don't get lashes. So that's a very reasonable position.
The fact that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said the only reason you
don't get lashes is because the positive מצוה mitzvah corrects it shows
that if you were just the fact that it was passive, you
would have gotten lashes. And the only reason you don't is because
the positive מצוה mitzvah corrected it. מכלל, Michlal, from this you can
infer דרבי יהודה סבר לוקין עליו, de-Rabbi Yehuda savar lokin alav, that
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you actually do get lashes for a
passive transgression, and therefore for the verbal act of taking an oath
or a vow you would get lashes because that was a concrete
prohibition, but for the generic prohibition of hugging and kissing and doing
other acts of honor which are not acts of worship, you would
actually not get lashes. Okay, I want to learn a little do
a little bit more to get the basic issue here about taking
a vow.
Very important. Okay, הנודר בשמו והמקיים בשמו הרי זה בלא תעשה. Ha-nodeir
bishmo ve-hamkayeim bishmo harei zeh belo taaseh. Now where do we know
that you're not allowed to do this?
הנודר בשמו והמקיים בשמו מנלן, Ha-nodeir bishmo ve-hamkayeim bishmo minalan, where do
you know that that's prohibited? Right? דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, ושם אלהים אחרים לא תזכירו. ve-sheim elohim acherim lo tazkiru.
You shall not mention the name of other gods. שלא יאמר אדם
לחבירו, She-lo yomar adam le-chaveiro, don't say to your friend, שמור לי
בצד עבודת כוכבים פלוני, shemor li be-tzad avodas kochavim peloni, go wait
for me by that idol of Zeus over there. Okay, so that
you've mentioned the name of another god. Now,
so that's what you get from not to mention. What do you
get from the verse לא ישמע על פיך, lo yishama al picha,
shall not be heard through your mouth? That seems just redundant. שלא
ידור בשמו ושלא יקיים בשמו. She-lo yidor bishmo ve-she-lo yekayeim bishmo. First
of all, it means a more weighty act, an act that you're
not just mentioning it but you're using it religiously. You're taking an
oath in the name of this god or you're vowing in the
name of this god. Okay, so that's now ולא, ve-lo, and the
other thing you learn from it is לא יגרום לאחרים שידירו בשמו.
lo yigrom le-acheirim she-yadiru bishmo. לא ישמע, Lo yishama, shall not be
heard through you means don't do something that makes somebody else sort
of use the name of the god in an oath. And these
אחרים acheirim are even non-Jews. Okay, what would be the case? So
דבר אחר, davar acher, לא ישמע על פיך, lo yishama al picha,
so we'll get back to what the case is in a minute,
but anyway, דבר אחר, davar acher, לא ישמע על פיך, lo yishama
al picha, אזהרה למסית ולמדיח. azhara le-meisis u-le-madiach. That's telling you where
do you know that the person who incites people for עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, where does it say you're not allowed to incite? I'm
not allowed to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Where does the Torah
ever tell me I get the death penalty, but where did it
tell me I'm not allowed to do it? לא ישמע על פיך
lo yishama al picha is you are causing other through your mouth
you're leading other people to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says one minute, מסית, meisis, when is the case of
מסית meisis somebody who incites an individual? בהדיא כתיבא, Be-hedya ksiva, it
says explicitly, וכל ישראל ישמעו ויראון ולא יוסיפו לעשות. Ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u
ve-yira'un ve-lo yosifu la'asos. You shall no longer
do this. Don't do this anymore. אלא אזהרה למדיח Ela azhara le-madiach
fine, but we don't have a verse that says that I'm not
allowed to incite a whole town to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
You could have maybe said that it's the same thing a thousand
times over but anyway. All right. Now now ולא יגרום לאחרים שידירו
בשמו ושמקיים בשמו. ve-lo yigrom le-acheirim she-yadiru bishmo ve-she-yekayimu bishmo. Now let's
get back to this thing, fine let's bracket מסית ומדיח. meisis u-madiach.
I'm not allowed to mention, I'm not allowed to take as an
oath, and I'm not allowed to make other people take it as
an oath. What's that example?
מסתייעא לאבא דשמואל, Mistayeia le-Abba de-Shmuel, this supports the father of Shmuel,
דאמר אבא דשמואל, de-amar Abba de-Shmuel, the father of Shmuel said, אסור
לאדם שיעשה שותפות עם העובד כוכבים. asur le-adam she-ya'aseh shutafus im ha-oved
kochavim. You're not allowed to go into partnership with an idolater non-Jewish
idolater.
Why not? שמא יתחייב לו שבועה She-ma yitchayeiv lo shvua because how
did you get people to make sure they were being honest? Right?
You didn't bring in these what do they call these, you know,
these accountants, what they call forensic accountants? No, what you did was
and checked all their receipts and emails. No, what you did is
you said make an oath for me that you did not steal
anything, right? That's how you kept people honest. So if you're with
an idolater and you say make an oath, they'll take an oath
in the name of their god. You then will have
transgressed לא ישמע על פיך. lo yishama al picha. Okay. שמא יתחייב
לו שבועה shema yitchayev lo shvua he'll be obligated a שבועה shvua
to you,
ונשבע בעבודת כוכבים שלו v'nishba b'avodas kochavim shelo he'll swear in the
name of his god, התורה אמרה לא ישמע על פיך haTorah amra
lo yishama al picha read it not be heard through your lips.
Now we'll stop here but I want to but before we do
I need to say two very important things about this or a
couple very important things. Number one, once you know you're not allowed
to take an oath, right, once you know you're not allowed to
even mention it, why do you need a פסוק pasuk to say
you can't take an oath? Today I can't make somebody else take
an oath, fine, but why do I need a פסוק pasuk to
say I can't take an oath if I'm not even allowed to
mention it? So the simplest answer is, and this is what רמבּם
Rambam says. רמבּם Rambam says like the real prohibition is using the
name of a god in a type of a religious way. Okay?
Is the taking of the oath and a vow. The idea that
you're also not allowed to mention it, that's like a secondary aspect,
maybe that's only your rabbinic aspect. The real part is the taking
of it in the name of in a religious context. That makes
a lot of sense. תוספות Tosafos seems to understand that even just
mentioning it is a biblical prohibition. And then this gets to real
questions, right, about, you know, saying the name of, you know, like
how we treat in general Christianity, or whatever. I've been saying Zeus
all along, how am I allowed to say Zeus? So that I'm
allowed to say because nobody nowadays treats it as a god. Now
there was a story in the הרב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik שיעור. shiur.
They were once talking about something and one of the students said,
you know, like that אותו האיש, oso ha'ish, ישו, Yeshu, whatever, the
Rav says, who are you talking about, Jesus? You know? So but
this avoidance, right, to say the name Jesus. But I don't have
a problem saying the name Jesus, but I don't say his last
name, you know, because the last name, whatever, is a name that
although technically the name just means Messiah, okay, but it's still a
name that is used to signify recognizing him as a god. It's
a godly name. That, you know, so I don't say that. I'm
very careful not to say that. Okay, but that's an interesting question,
right, what are the parameters of לא ישמע על פיך? lo yishama
al picha? Right? Can you only do I only if if when
I say it I don't mean it that way, you know, or
no, saying a name that for people carries the weight of signifying
a divine designation, and there are people that still, you know, treat
it that way, is that the prohibition? It sounds like at least
a rabbinic violation of לא ישמע על פיך. lo yishama al picha.
So that's like one really important issue. The other really important thing,
once we're talking about Christianity, I know it's funny to all do
this at the last minute,
is how did Jews go into partnership with Christians if they would
take an oath? So let's take a let's look at this last
תוספות. Tosafos. If you can give me three more minutes, I want
to just read this last תוספות. Tosafos. Very important about attitudes towards
Christianity. תוספות Tosafos says אסור לאדם שיעשה שותפות. assur l'adam she'ya'aseh shutafus.
אמר רבי שמואל. Amar Rabbi Shmuel. כל שכן שבועה עצמה דאין לקבל
מהם. kol sheken shvua atzma d'ein l'kabel mehem. So certainly therefore you
can't even go in partnership lest you take an oath from him.
You're certainly not allowed to take an oath from a non-Jew. Now
that means there're cases you would have to take an oath even
if you weren't in partnership. Let's say for example you lent him
money and he was denying whether he had paid you back or
whatever the case might be. So this says, okay, you can't take
any oaths from him because you'll cause him to make this oath
in the name of their god. רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam אומר מותר
לקבל מהם שבועה. omer mutar l'kabel mehem shvua. No, you're allowed to
take an oath from a Christian, that was the context, קודם שיפסיד
kodem she'yafsid so to save yourself from losing money. כדי אמרינן בפרק
קמא דמסכת עבודה זרה, ki'di'amrinan b'perek kama d'masechet avoda zara, דמלוה על
פניו פורעין הימנו מפני שהוא כמציל מידם. d'malveh al panav porin heimenu
mipnei she'hu k'matzil mi'yadam. You can collect a debt even before their
holiday because you're saving your money. Now how is that permissible if
it's a biblical violation? ולא חיישינן דאזיל ומודה. v'lo chaishinan d'azil u'modeh.
I don't want to get into that, that's an issue about before
their holiday. Okay, now I'm just skipping a line. מכל מקום בזמן
הזה והחבאד. mi'kol makom bizman hazeh v'hachbad. He says now they definitely
are going to take an oath in the name of their god
and that's a biblical violation.
מכל מקום בזמן הזה כולם נשבעים בקדשים שלהם mi'kol makom bizman hazeh
kulam nishba'in b'kadashim shelohem ואין תופסים בהם אלוהות. v'ein tofsim bahem elohut.
He says no, nowadays they don't take an oath in the name
of their god. They take an oath in the name of their
קדשים. kadashim. What do you think קדשים kadashim means?
Saints. In their, okay, in the name of saint so-and-so. I swear
by saint so-and-so. So they don't think of their saints as divine.
So it's not the name of another god. So תוספות Tosafos says,
oh, you're actually saved. Phew! It was not the name of another
god. That's why you can do it. Then they don't treat them
as gods. ואף על פי שמשתפים עמהם שם שמים v'af al pi
she'meshatefim imahem shem shamayim now וכונתם לדבר אחר, v'kavanatam l'davar acher, the
original text supposedly said וכונתם לישו. v'kavanatam l'Yeshu. Even though but they
don't just say saint so-and-so. They say in the name of God
and saint so-and-so, right? So
when they say God, on the one hand that's not שם אלוהים
אחרים. shem elohim acherim. They say God. The problem isn't the name
is the name of another god. The problem is וכונתם
לדבר אחר. kavanatam l'davar acher. When they say God, they're thinking about
Jesus. So saying saint so-and-so
isn't. Such a great תוספות Tosafos for our attitude towards Christianity says
מכל מקום
אין זה שם עבודת כוכבים.
mikol makom
ein zeh shem avodas kochavim. He says number one they didn't say
Jesus. They said God. So the name, you know, the name they're
using is a name that we would use to refer to God
as well. It's not the name of a different God. Number one.
How about what that name refers to? So he says even what
the name refers to isn't such a problem. גם דעתם לאביהם שבשמים.
gam daatam l'avihem shebashamayim. Meaning when they say God they're talking about
God the Father. They're not actually talking about Jesus. So actually you're
fine. Saint so-and-so isn't a God. God on the one hand the
word is an okay word. It's not a word that's only and
number two even what it refers to is a God concept we
agree with. Okay so you're totally safe. Okay. If they would say
a name a name of Jesus you got a problem but now
you're safe. Wait he says there's one last issue. Okay he says
okay ואף על פי שמשתפים שם שמים ודבר אחר. v'af al pi
shemeshatafim shem shamayim v'davar acher. Ah remember what we just said in
the previous עמוד? amud? How about the fact that the Christian is
saying God and saint so-and-so? So they're putting God and the saint
in the same category. Okay they're combining God with something else. Isn't
that a problem? Right? We just mentioned that a minute ago. He
says no. ועל כאן דאסור לגרום לאחרים לשתף. v'al kan d'asur ligrom
l'acherim l'shatef. You're prohibited to get a non-Jew to swear in the
name of a foreign god. That we learned. There's no way that
you're prohibited to make a non-Jew use God's name together with a
saint's name. Right? That's not something that we're prohibited in doing. ולפני
עיוור ליכא. v'lifnei iver leika. And we're not even we're not even
causing them to sin. Why? דבני נח לא הוזהרו בכך. d'vnei Noach
lo huzharu bekach. Non-Jews are forbidden to worship other gods. They're never
told you're not allowed to combine God's name with a saint's name.
Okay so we're totally safe. A saint isn't the name of another
god. God isn't the name of another god. It doesn't even refer
to another god. And combining God and the saint's name. That would
be a problem for us to put them all in the same
sort of you know use as an oath giving them equal status
as it were but it's not a prohibition for them. So we're
totally safe. Okay so this is a lovely little תוספות Tosafos about
how you can make them take an oath. It's also fascinating because
it recognizes an area of commonality with Jews and Christians. Even to
the degree that we've classically you know in the period of תוספות
Tosafos Christianity was עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But it says you know
there's an aspect of it when they say God and are thinking
about God the Father, they're actually all talking about the same thing.
Right? It's only when they talk about Jesus and so on that
we're talking about different things. So that's important. But the other way
this תוספות Tosafos was extremely important and although this seems to have
not been תוספות's Tosafos intention at all was that תוספות Tosafos was
read to say when תוספות Tosafos says they combine God with something
else in the context of תוספות Tosafos it means they say God
and saint so-and-so and he says that's not a problem for non-Jews.
But how else do you think that could have been read that
saying when they combine God and something else it's not a problem?
It doesn't mean when they take an oath that says God and
saint so-and-so. What other combining of God and something else might Christians
do? They combine God with the other parts of the Trinity. Right?
So a way this תוספות Tosafos was read and became extremely this
misread extremely influential in הלכה halacha in a whole הלכה halacha halachic
approach to Christianity is that even if we say Christianity is עבודה
זרה avodah zarah it's עבודה זרה avodah zarah for us. But the
way but for them to combine an idea of God as creator
of heaven and earth and God the Father with other components like
you know with you know the Son and the Holy Ghost or
whatever for them that's not a problem. That's not עבודה זרה avodah
zarah for them as long as they have that idea of God
creator transcendent God other things they throw in it's not עבודה זרה
avodah zarah for them. For us it would be עבודה זרה avodah
zarah but not for them. Now again that's not what תוספות Tosafos
was saying. תוספות Tosafos was saying if you take an oath and
you say God and saint so-and-so a pagan non a pagan takes
that oath or a Christian takes that oath that's not a transgression
to use both in an oath. But תוספות Tosafos is read to
say it's not actually a violation of their prohibition of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah if they combine the God concept with oh whoop with
other types of concepts. Okay so oh one second. Anyway
a lot of very important ideas here at the end okay particularly
a question about what is the scope for us of mentioning the
name of other gods even if it's not in a religious context?
Just saying you know like I said you know I mean Zeus.
I said Zeus because nobody worships Zeus but saying the name of
some other god. If I can just say it like can I
talk about other religions and the names of their god or does
it have to carry some particular weight you know for me to
transgress? Is it a biblical transgression or rabbinic transgression? And then this
really important תוספות Tosafos about not only taking oaths but areas of
when you know of overlap you know of Even when you're judging
Christianity to be עבודה זרה *Avodah zarah*, when you say God, there's
actually is basically a shared area of belief, and then a way
that this תוספות *Tosafos* was used to actually radically redefine how הלכה
*halacha* sees Christianity, that at least from the- it's not what תוספות
*Tosafos* was saying, but it became- it was interpreted to mean that
at least from the perspective from non-Jews in terms of the מצוות
בני נח *mitzvos bnei noach*, combining the God concept with other aspects
would actually not be a violation. That's at least the way that
תוספות *Tosafos* was read. Okay, we will pick up with this tomorrow.
So there's a problem with studying other